Agnese Bartolucci

Visual Designer and PhD Candidate

agnesebartolucci505@gmail.com (+39) 3478257568 Helsinki, FI

Portfolio | Linkedin | Behance

I am a freelance visual designer with professional experience in information and data visualization, UX/UI, and print design. I excel in managing complex projects from concept to delivery, crafting cohesive visual identities, and devising innovative design solutions that are accessible yet visually pleasing.

Areas of expertise

- → Visual Design
- → Information and Data Visualization
- → UX/UI and Interaction Design
- → Printed and Editorial Design
- → Visual Identity Development
- → Visual Reference Curation
- → Concept Development
- → Cross-Media Communication
- → Qualitative and Design Research
- → Academic Writing
- → Digital Archives
- → Intersectional Feminism

Technical skills

- → Expert: Illustrator, InDesign, Photoshop, Lightroom, Figma, HTML, CSS, Excel/Google Sheets, Keynote/PowerPoint, RAWGraphs, Gephi.
- → **Proficient**: P5.is, Tableau, OpenRefine.
- → Basic knowledge: Pr, Ae, ¡Query, D3.js, QGIS.

Languages

- → Italian: Mothertongue
- → English: Proficient IELTS Academic 7.5 (C1) Date 23/02/2023

Soft skills

- → Presentation. Experienced in presenting design projects to both internal and external audiences.
- → **Teamwork**. Experienced in working with teams and collaborating with diverse professionals.
- → **Planning**. Capable of delivering projects on time through planning and organisation.
- → **Problem-solving**. Ability to find innovative solutions to problems with a focus on efficacy.
- **Creativity**. Developed concepts from a brief through a multi-step process, including research and error-based trials.

Work experience

JANUARY 2024 - PRESENT

INT-ACT - Doctoral Researcher and Visual Designer

Supporting researchers in studying emotional, experiential, and environmental dimensions of intangible cultural heritage through data analysis and promotional material design.

- → Analyzing narrative interview transcripts using thematic analysis
- → Designing the website to promote and aggregate materials

JANUARY 2023 - PRESENT

The Visual Agency, Milano - Graphic and Data Visualisation Designer (Freelance)

Collaborating with a data visualization and information design company to develop publications for UN agencies and corporations.

- → Designing reports, from layout to data visualization, autonomously
- → Selecting and curating media for publications from databases

OCTOBER 2023 - DECEMBER 2023

Aalto University, Espoo - Tutor

Participated in the ideation and implementation of the Code Clinic course for the Information Design minor to introduce students to data visualization tools and JavaScript.

- → Taught lessons on data visualization design and tools
- → Developed teaching materials, including presentations and hands-on tutorials

JANUARY - APRIL 2021

Accurat, Milano - Data Visualization Designer

Contributed to the data visualization team focused on reporting and

- → Designed weekly dashboards for printed newspapers
- → Collaborated on data visualization projects, such as data posters and reports

JUNE - SEPTEMBER 2019

La Biennale di Venezia, Venezia - Graphic Designer

Contributed to the Publishing and Web Office, handling communication and advertising for the cultural institution.

- → Developed written and visual material for social networks
- → Designed printed materials for the International Venice Film Festival

APRIL - SEPTEMBER 2019

Politecnico di Milano, DEIB, Milano - Graphic Designer

Created communication materials for the Communication Office, ensuring technical and promotional content was visually appealing and organized.

- → Developed visual identities and promotional materials for various events
- → Designed presentations and presentation templates for multiple purposes

Education

SEPTEMBER 2023 - PRESENT

Department of Art and Media, Aalto University **Doctoral Student**

Pursuing a PhD within the Visual Communication Design Research Group, focusing on a practice-based research project aimed at diversifying perspectives in digital archives through the lens of intersectional feminism under the supervision of Dr. Masood Masoodian.

SEPTEMBER 2018 - APRIL 2022

M.Sc. in Communication Design, Politecnico di Milano Master's Degree (110 cum laude/110)

Developed a research-based methodology and consolidated competencies in communication design, with a focus on game design, cross-media communication, UX/UI design, and information and data visualization design, from data collection to implementation.

SEPTEMBER 2015 - JULY 2018

Bachelor in Communication Design, Politecnico di Milano Bachelor's Degree (108/110)

Gained expertise in visual representation and graphic techniques, creating various editorial and digital products, corporate identities, and websites.